U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers 5087
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers
1907-1954
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
U.S. National Mediation Board
Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee
Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (BLE)
5087
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Briefs and exhibits of Arbitration Board No. 192. Carriers represented by the Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committees and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, 1907- 1954.
3116761
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, February 04, 2013
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 07, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Carriers represented by the Eastern, Western and South Eastern Carriers' Conference Committees and their employees represented by the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers, Arbitration Board No. 192, N M.B. Case A-4400, April 26, 1954 (Engineers 30% Wage Case.)
The controversy arose out of notices served by the union on the various carriers for a percentage wage increase which would correspond with increases made in other industries and restore the relative percentage of differential in pay which had existed between engineers and firemen.
The carriers submitted a package proposal which was substantially identical with that offered to the firemen and trainmen; to include the cost of living adjustment in the basic rate, and an increase of five cents per hour,
Unable to reach an agreement, the Brotherhood request- ed the carriers to join it in invoking the services the National Mediation Board. After several days of proceedings the N.M.B. persuaded the parties to submit their controversies to arbitration. An Arbitration Agreement was signed and the controversy submitted to a Board consisting of Archibald Cox, Chairman, Richard A. Lester, J.W. Oram, D.P. Loomis, Donald S. Beattle and Thomas J. Harkins.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5081: U.S. National Mediation Board United Air Lines Findings 5082: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcript of Hearings Regarding the BRAC 5083: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding United Air Lines and Air Line Pilots Association 5085: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding American Air Lines and Transport Workers Union of America 5086: U.S. National Mediation Board Transcripts Regarding New York Central Railroad Company and BRAC 5088: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Eastern, Western, and Southeastern Carriers' Conference Committee and the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers 5089: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding General Managers Association of New York and the International Longshoremen's Association, Lighter Captains Union, Local 996 5090: U.S. National Mediation Board Records Regarding Chicago and Northwestern Railway Company et al. and the Order of Railroad Telegraphers 5579: National Mediation Board Emergency Board 180, Train Crew Consists 5748 OHM: National Mediation Board Airline Industry Arbitration Oral History Interviews 5806: U.S. National Mediation Board Agreements
Arbitration, Industrial -- United States -- Sources; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States -- Sources; United States. National Mediation Board. Arbitration Board No. 192; United States. National Mediation Board; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers--Sources.
3116761
- Briefs on Behalf of the Carriers (3 Volumes) (Box 1)
  - Pattern Settlements (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adequacy of Engineers' Earnings (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Historical Development of the Earnings of Engineers (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Characteristics of the Work of Engineers and Other Classes of Operating Employees (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Factors Responsible for the Changes in Relationships between the Earnings of Engineers and Other Classes of Employees (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Changes in Wage Differentials (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Relative Earnings of Newly Promoted Engineers and Job Preferences (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Attitude of Employees Regarding Promotion (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Economic Brief on Behalf of the Carriers (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brief of the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Opening Statement of Guy L. Brown, Grand Chief Engineer (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - List of Appearances (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Index of Witnesses (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Agreement, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Scope and Contents
    August 17, 1954
- Carrier Exhibits (Box 2)
  - The appearances for the Carriers (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Standard Basic Rates - Engineers Road and Yard Service, 1915-1953 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Standard Basic Rates - Firemen and Hostlers - Road and Yard Service, 1915-1953 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Standard Basic Rates - Conductors and Trainmen Road and Yard Service, 1915-1953 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Earnings of Railroad Engineers, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Earnings of Railroad Engineers, 1st Supplement., 1954 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Rules Governing the Classification of Railroad Employees, Reports of their Service and Compensation (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Wage Movement, 1953-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Pattern Settlements in the Railroad Industry, 1937-1953 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Wage Differentials (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Differentials - Wage Rates and Earnings (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Differentials - Wage Rates and Earnings, 1st Supplement (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Differentials - Wage Rates and Earnings, 2nd Supplement. (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Excerpts from Report of the Eight-Hour Commission (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - The Rates and Bases of Pay and Working Conditions of Engineers and Firemen, 1907-1953 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Volume I: 1907-1940. Volume II: 1941-1953. 15a. Miscellaneous agreements, Data and Excerpts from Records of Proceedings.
  - Documents and Letters Pertaining to Supplement Number 15 to General Order Number 27 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - History of the Diesel Rules Movement prior to the Second and Third Diesel Cases, 1933-1949 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    November 1933-January 1949
  - Documents, Letters, and Data Pertaining to the Diesel Agreement of January 25, 1944 between the Western Carriers and the Employees Represented by the Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Statement Showing Certain Details of the Working Conditions and Arbitrary Payments Enjoyed by Engineers, Chicago, Burlington, and Quincy Railroad (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Earnings Data - Engineers' Extra Boards (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Job Preference Studies. (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Job Preference Studies (Supplements). (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Age Groups of Locomotive Engineers; Earnings of Locomotive Engineers 65 Years of Age and Over (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Engineers' Job. (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Material Relating to Promotions Terminal Railroad Association of Saint Louis. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Material Relating to Promotions, Saint Louis Southwestern Railway Lines. (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Map of Louisville and Nashville Lines. (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Louisville and Nashville Railroad Miscellaneous Data (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Louisville and Nashville Railroad Firemen's Seniority Rosters. (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Louisville and Nashville Railroad, Engineers Seniority Rosters (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Seaboard Air Line Railroad Company - Number of Men in Engine Service (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Comparisons of Casualties and Casualty Rates of Engineers and Other Operating Employees in Road and Yard Service (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Service and Earnings of Engineers on the Extra Board (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Seaboard Air Line Railroad Company - Number of Men in Engine Service (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Chicago Milwaukee, Saint Paul, and Pacific Railroad Company (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - The Railroad Financial Situation (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Long term trends, railroads and other industries. (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Train studies. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Supplemental material relating to the current wage movement. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Statement showing number of Promoted Engineers (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Louisville and Nashville Railroad: Economic and Financial Data (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Illustrative Examples of Mountain and Desert Differentials Paid to Engineers (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Total Number of Enginemen and Enginemen Assigned to Passenger Service (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Statement of William White before Emergency Board 106 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    February 19, 1954
  - Supplement to Carriers Exhibit Number 36: The Railroad Financial Situation. (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Analysis of Increase in Straight Time Hourly Earnings Engineers and Firemen (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Union Exhibits (Box 3)
  - Wage Request Notice (page 120) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letter (page 130), 1954 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    January 12, 1954
  - Letter (page 131), 1954 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    January 13, 1954
  - Agreement (page 144), 1952 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    May 23, 1952
  - Amended Agreement (page 146) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Basic Rates - Engineers (page 150) (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Basic Rates - Firemen (page 150) (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Release - Association of American Railroads (page 156) (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Rules - Chicago and Northwest Transportation Company (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - "Rules Jersey Central." - New York and Long Branch (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - "Rules Erie" (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - "Rules Santa Fe" (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - "Timetable Chicago and North Western" (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - "Timetable Baltimore and Ohio" (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Timetable New York City" (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Timetable Pennsylvania Railroad" (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "Timetable Pennsylvania Railroad, Phila Terminal" (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "Timetable Central Railroad of New Jersey" (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Timetable, Reading" (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "Differentials" (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - "Difference - Rates and Earnings" (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Cost of Living Adjustments" (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - "Occupational Wage Differentials" (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Engineers' Wage Differentials" (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Engineers' Wage Differentials (Not Narrowed)" (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Engineer Wage Differentials (Why and How)" (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Jones Book" (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "History of Differentials" (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "Steps - Collective Bargaining" (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Wage Comparisons" (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Letter (page 625) (Box 3, Folder 31)
    February 23, 1954. 31a. "Wadlow to Davisson." 31b. Letter - November (page 625). 31c. "Wadlow to Beattie."
  - "Different Average Earnings" (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - "United States Steel - Job Titles" (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - "Bureau of Labor Statistics Wage Chronologies" (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "Re-establishing Railroad Engineers' Wage Differentials" (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "Revised Table 50" (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - "Revised Table 51" (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "Bulletin Number 1883, March 21, 1950" (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - "Wage Increases of Railroad Engineers" (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Newspaper Clippings (page 1053) (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - No information available (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - "Differential change" (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - "Adv - Salina, Kansas, May 5, 1954" (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - "Seniority Roster - Allegheny Division" (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - "Price Movement - Dow Jones Averages" (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - "Annual report - 1953 Milwaukee Road" (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - "The Positive Side of the Tracks" (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - "Current Assets and Liabilities, Selected companies" (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - "Trend in Prices, Pennsylvania Railroad and Others" (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - "107th Annual Report of the Pennsylvania Railroad" (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - "Excerpts - Emergency Board Report September 25, 1943" (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - "Annual Report of the Louisville and Nashville Railroad Company, 1953" (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - "National Income Originating in Transportation and Communication Industries 1939 and 1952", 1939-1952 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    1939 and 1952.
  - "Railroads' Financial Strength" (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - "Plights of the Railroads" (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - "Statements concerning future outlook from Carriers Annual Reports for 1953" (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - "Summary of Court and Commission Cases on Rate of Return" (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - "Percent Earned on Net Property - 1953" (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - "Wage Differentials to Railroad Engineers" Rebuttal Exhibit (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Reports Number 3503, 3526, 3533, 3546, 3510, 3532, 3540, and 3551 marked 60-A to 60-C respectively. Reports Numbers 3257, 3265, 3242, and 3281 marked 60-H through 60-K, respectively. Reports Numbers 3437 and 3419 Exparte Numbers 178, 181, 186 marked 60L t (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - Letter from Whitmire to Davison, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    June 24, 1954
  - "Assignment Sheets, Locomotive Firemen, Term." Railroad Association of Saint Louis, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    June 23, 1954.
  - "Table Number 1 - Changes in Hourly Wage Rates, Day Shifts, Chicago Printing Industry." (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - "The Future - What Jim Sims Is Doing About It" (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - "Mr Unterberger's Comments" (Box 3, Folder 65)
- Transcripts of Proceedings (Box 4)